跳舞小人案
艾尔西 出什么事了?
Elsie, what's the matter?
艾尔西
Elsie!
看来 华生
So, Watson.
你不打算投资南非证券了?
You do not propose to invest in South African securities?
你怎么什么都知道?
How on earth do you know that?
好了 承认吧 你是大吃了一惊吧
Now, confess, you are utterly taken aback.
当然
I am!
我就该让你立字为据
I should make you sign a paper to that effect.
为什么?
Why?
因为要不了几分钟 你就会说 这也太简单了点
In a few minutes you will say it is all so absurdly simple.
我可说不出这样的话来
I should say nothing of the kind!
你要知道 我亲爱的华生 作出一连串的推理来
You see, my dear Watson, it is not really difficult
其实算不上什么难题
to construct a series of inferences,
这些推理环环相扣
each dependent upon its predecessor
每一步又都清晰明了
and each simple in itself.
然后 只要把中间的环节一笔抹去
If after doing so one simply knocks out the central inferences
只交代给观众
and presents one's audience
他的出发点和结论
with the starting point and the conclusion,
就能看到别人瞠目结舌的样子了
one may produce a startling,
不过 这也许不过是哗众取宠而已
though possibly a meretricious, effect.
我是通过观察你
I can tell by an inspection of the groove
左手虎口处
between your left forefinger and thumb,
得知你不打算把你那一小笔资金
that you have decided not to invest your small capital
投到金矿中去
in the gold fields.
我可看不出这有什么关系
I can see no connection.
貌似是没有
Very likely not;
不过我这就给你看密切的联系
but I can quickly give you a close connection.
简单的线索 串起缺失的环节
Here are the missing links in the very simple chain:
你昨晚从俱乐部回来
You had chalk between your forefinger and thumb
左手虎口处粘有白色粉末
when you returned from the club last night.
你只有打台球时 为了减少球杆阻力 才会抹白粉
You put chalk there when you play billiards, to ease the cue.
而没有瑟斯顿作伴 你不会打台球
You never play billiards except with Thurston.
四周之前 你告诉过我 瑟斯顿
Now, Thurston, you told me, four weeks ago,
有买卖某南非证券的特权
had an option on some South African security
下个月就作废
which expired in a month,
而他很想和你一同经营
and which he desired you to share with him.
你把支票簿锁在我抽屉里
Your checkbook is locked in my drawer,
也没问我要钥匙
and you have not asked for the key.
所以说 你不打算对此投资
So, you do not propose to invest your money in that manner.
这也太简单了点
How absurdly simple!
一点不假
Quite so.
只要跟你解释过 什么问题都变简单了
Every problem is absurdly simple when it is explained to you.
福尔摩斯 你干吗这么高兴?
Holmes, why are you so cheerful?
你正在待业 没案子可破
You're unemployed, you have no case to solve.
换在平时 你肯定心情低落
Now, normally that produces black moods
凄凄惨惨 以可卡因消愁
and the infernal lethargy of the cocaine bottle.
你就是不懂什么是逻辑思维
You have not used the logical principles
亏我整天跟你耳提面命
which I constantly expound.
福尔摩斯展目舒眉
Sherlock Holmes is cheerful,
那就是说 夏洛克福尔摩斯大案在手
so, Sherlock Holmes must have a case.
对了
Pa!
看看你能看出什么门道来 华生老友
See what you can make of that, friend Watson.
福尔摩斯 这不就是小孩的涂鸦吗?
Why, Holmes, it's a child's drawing.
你就是这么想的?
Ah, is that your idea?
那还能是什么?
Well, what else should it be?
这位达比郡瑞都岭镇庄园的
Well, that is what a Mr. Hilton Cubitt,
希尔顿丘比特先生也很想知道
of Ridling Thorpe Manor, Darbyshire, is anxious to know.
这个谜是早班邮件送到的
That conundrum came by the first post,
他本人坐随后的火车赶来
and he is to follow by the next train.
希尔顿丘比特
Hilton Cubitt.
别费事了 我都查过了 华生
No, no, I have already looked him up, Watson.
他的家族在达比郡拥有领地已经有500年了
His family has owned land in Darbyshire for over 500 years,
所以我想 丘比特先生一定有财有势
so I presume that Mr. Cubitt is as respectable as he is worthy.
容光焕发 神朗气清
With a fresh face, an open countenance,
还戴着棕色圆顶礼帽
and wearing a brown bowler hat.
别开玩笑了 你怎么可能知道这么详细
Oh, no, you cannot possibly know that.
不相信 福尔摩斯?
Really, Holmes?
你会留在这儿记录案子吧?
Uh, you will stay and keep a record of the case?
赴汤蹈火
My dear fellow.
多谢 哈德逊太太
Thank you, Mrs. Hudson.
这边请 丘比特先生
This way, Mr. Cubitt.
我就是夏洛克福尔摩斯
Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
希尔顿丘比特
Hilton Cubitt.
这是我的好友兼同事华生大夫
And this is my friend and colleague, Dr. Watson.
华生大夫 你好
Dr. Watson, sir.
荣幸之至 请坐吧 丘比特先生
How do you do? Do sit down, Mr. Cubitt.
谢谢
Thank you.
什么结果 先生们 你们觉得这东西是什么?
So, what do you make of it, gentlemen? This thing.
您研究过了吗?
Have you had time to study it?
可笑的小人排着队跳舞
Absurd little figures dancing in a line,
孩子信笔涂抹的结果
it's a childish prank.
这点小事 你为什么觉得重要?
Why do you attach importance to something so trivial?
不是我 福尔摩斯
I don't, Mr. Holmes.
我肯定不会
I-I never should.
其实...是我的妻子
No, it's-it'sit's my wife, you see.
她...
She-
尽管说 丘比特先生 都不是外人
Go on, Mr. Cubitt, you're with friends.
这东西吓得她要命
But it's-it's frightened her almost to death.
她什么都不说 装作若无其事
She says nothing, tries to appear normal,
但我从没见过谁会这么慌张
but I've never seen anyone so upset.
这和原先用白粉笔画在院子长椅上的一模一样?
In white chalk on a garden seat, it is a precise copy?
我尽可能画得一模一样了
Oh, it's as exact as I could make it.
我的确以为是马童画的
I did think it might be the stable boy,
但那孩子说没画过
but the lad denied it.
要是我妻子有危险 福尔摩斯先生
If there's any danger threatening my wife, Mr. Holmes,
我倾家荡产也要保护她
I'd spend my last penny to protect her.
丘比特先生 您请坐吧
Do sit down, Mr. Cubitt.
抽烟吗 丘比特先生?
Do you smoke, Mr. Cubitt?
好的
Uh, yes.
哦 不 不 我不抽 谢谢
Uh, no, no, no, I won't, thank you.
说说您夫人吧 丘比特先生
Tell us about your wife, Mr. Cubitt.
好吧 我一直都住在达比郡
Well, uh, I've always lived in Darbyshire,
靠近马特洛克的瑞都岭镇庄园里
Ridling Thorpe Manor, near Matlock.
我一直是个单身汉 要不是三年前
I was a bachelor and thought I'd remain one
去了趟伦敦 还以为会一辈子孤家寡人了
until three years ago I came down to London on a visit.
真是做梦也没想到
It's a rare thing for me, but-
我是打算去看看女王即位五十周年大典
well, I had a mind to see the Queen's Golden Jubilee.
我在罗素广场有寄宿处
I put up at a boardinghouse in Russell Square,
因为帕克 我们的教区牧师
because Parker, he's the vicar of our parish,
他待在那儿
he was staying there.
当时在那儿的还有一位年轻的美国姑娘
There was also a young American lady staying there,
她姓帕特里克 艾尔西帕特里克
Patrick was her name, Elsie Patrick.
我们都没个伴儿 就交上了朋友
We were both alone, and we became friends,
一起结伴同游之类
did the sites and that.
你出的钱?
At your expense?
当然不是
Certainly not.
你难不成以为...
Are you suggesting-
没有 丘比特先生 绝无此意
No, he's not, Mr. Cubitt, not at all.
这位帕特里克小姐来伦敦 就为看女王大典?
Was this Miss Elsie Patrick in London merely for the Jubilee?
不 不 不是 她到伦敦有一阵子了
No, no, no, she'd been here some time.
她厌倦了美国 四处游历
She'd tired of America, traveled about,
最后在英国落了脚
and finally settled in England.
不用多说了 等到假期结束
Well, not to make a labor of it, before my holiday was over,
我就成了个恋爱中的男人
I was as much in love as any man ever has been.
让我喜出望外的是 她...
To my surprise and joy, she-
她和我两情相悦 我们就结了婚
she reciprocated my feelings, and we were married.
善莫大焉
Excellent.
没张扬 就去登了个记
Quietly, in ain a Register Office.
你准是当我疯了 福尔摩斯先生 没认识两天
You think I'm mad, Mr. Holmes, taking a wife in such a fashion,
心血来潮就把婚结了?
knowing nothing about her?
解释吧 丘比特先生 说重点
Explain, Mr. Cubitt, and come to the point!
哦 是的 其实 就在我们结婚那天
Oh, uh, yes, in fact, it was on the very day of our marriage.
那时我觉得一切都好 没有一丝不快
Nothing could have made me unhappy, nothing on that day.
但现在想想 还真有些奇怪
But now I look back, it was odd.
艾尔西?
Elsie?
有些话我得跟你说 希尔顿
There is something I have to say to you, Hilton.
我们可别晚了 亲爱的
We don't want to be late, my dear.
我一直拖到现在
I've put it off till now.
但我还是要给你个重新考虑的机会
But I must still give you the chance to change your mind.
艾尔西 有这么严重吗?
Elsie, what in the world?
听我说完
Let me finish!
我说的字字属实
And what I say, I do mean.
我很爱你
I love you dearly,
但你对我之前的经历一无所知
but you know nothing of my life before we met.
我没有问啊
I never asked.
这也是我这么爱你的原因之一
One of the things which has made me so fond of you.
如果你娶了我 希尔顿 我保证 你娶的女人
If you marry me, Hilton, I promise you marry a woman
从没有做过任何事会让你感到羞耻
who has nothing personally to be ashamed of.
但你要按我说的做
But you'll have to take my word for it,
永远不要过问
and allow me to be silent forever
我们相遇前我的生活
as to my life before we met.
要是你觉得这太过分
If that's too much to ask,
那还是请您回达比郡
then you must go back to your Darbyshire
留下我一个人 就当未曾遇见过您
and leave me to the lonely life in which you found me.
一点不过分 我永远不会让你离开我
It's little enough to ask, and I shall never let you go.
就这样 我度过了最幸福的三年
These have been the happiest three years of my life.
那么 自何时起
And when did the first cloud
开始有愁云蔽日呢?
cover the sun of this great happiness?
您还真一针见血 福尔摩斯先生
You have a way of putting things, Mr. Holmes.
您也很擅长
And you have a way
顾左右而言他 丘比特先生
of prevaricating with your answers, Mr. Cubitt.
好吧 是几个月前 确切的说是五月
Well, it was, uh, some months ago, May in fact.
希尔顿?
Hilton?!
来了
Hello!
在这儿 客厅
Here, in the drawing room!
看看 喜欢吗?
Well, what do you think?
真不错 焕然一新了
Yes, great improvement!
谢谢 桑德斯
Thank you, Saunders.
我遇见了邮差 没让他再跑一趟
I met the postman, saved him a journey.
有账单
Here's a bill.
还有封你的信 美国邮戳 从芝加哥
Here's one for you, an American stamp, Chicago.
希望午饭好了 我饿死了
I hope lunch is ready, I'm ravenous.
她烧掉了信 拆都没拆?
She burned the letter, unopened?
是啊 我不知道为什么
Yes, I don't know why.
你当然不知道
Of course you don't.
美国是她的过去 是你不容打破的誓言
America is her past, and the subject of a solemn promise.
是啊 可从那以后 她就一直心神不定
Yes, but she's not had an easy hour from that moment.
要是她信得过我
If only she'd trust me.
我对她是一百个信任 这点你得相信我
Now, I have every faith in her, you must believe that.
不管她的过去怎么样 我肯定那都不是她的错
Whatever there was in her past, I'm sure it's no fault of hers.
说说跳舞的小人
And the dancing men?
哦 好吧
Oh, yes,
我以为她已经忘了那封信的事了
well, I thought she was getting over the letter,
结果这些小人又跳出来了
and then thesethese drawings appeared.
不过就是孩子随笔乱画
It's just a childish scrawl,
可什么都每况愈下了
but it made everything worse than before.
我可不能就这么看着
Well, I couldn't just leave it.
这事还不能跟警察说
And it wasn't the sort of thing I could take to the police
他们准会笑话我
for they would have laughed at me,
所以我来找你了
so I've come to you.
丘比特先生 您想过没有
Don't you think, Mr. Cubitt,
最好的解决办法
that your best plan would be
就是直接问您的夫人
to make a direct appeal to your wife,
请她与您分担心中的秘密?
and ask her to share her secret with you?
君子一言 驷马难追 福尔摩斯先生
A promise is a promise, Mr. Holmes.
要是艾尔西打算告诉我 她会的
If Elsie wishes to tell me, then she will.
我可没这个权利去打听隐私
But I have no right to force a confidence.
不过 作为丈夫 我也会尽职尽责的 我会的
However, I do feel entitled to take my own line, and I will.
那我也会全力以赴帮助您的
Then I will help you with all my heart.
您有没有看到附近有什么陌生人出现过?
Have you seen or heard of any strangers in the neighborhood?
没有 没见过
No, no, I haven't.
有些农户会收些房客
Some of the farmers take in lodgers,
不过最近倒是没怎么听说
but I've not heard of any lately.
那我建议您先回达比郡吧 丘比特先生
Then I suggest that you return to Darbyshire, Mr. Cubitt,
眼睛放亮些
and keep a sharp lookout.
再有新的跳舞小人
And make an exact copy
一定要准确无误地记下给我
of any fresh dancing men that may appear.
谢谢 福尔摩斯先生 我会的
Thank you, Mr. Holmes. I will.
对了 丘比特先生
Oh, and Mr. Cubitt,
让您夫人辗转难侧的那第一封信
this letter which started your wife's torment,
您确信是从美国寄来的?
you are quite certain that it was from the United States?
没错 邮戳是芝加哥
Yeah, the postmark was Chicago.
再会 不用担心
Goodbye! And don't worry.
她从美国收到信件
It's perfectly natural
也没什么不正常的
she should receive a letter from America,
她不就是美国来的
she's from America.
没错 但拆都没拆就烧掉就不正常了
Yes, but it is not natural to throw it onto the fire unopened.
这么看上去还有点像旗语了
It's beginning to look like semaphore.
你读了我写的密码专论了?
You have read my monograph on secret ciphers?
翻了翻
Some of it.
读起来太艰深了
I found it rather heavy going.
不用问 这肯定代表着什么
It evidently has a meaning.
这要真是信手画的 那可就是匪夷所思了
If it is purely arbitrary, it may be impossible to solve.
不过 只要这有规可循
However, if it is systematic,
我们就能拨开云雾见青天
we should be able to get to the bottom of it.
但我们还需要更多的信息 越长越好
But we need more messages, and preferably long ones.
我觉得希尔顿丘比特可不这么希望
Well, I doubt if Hilton Cubitt would agree with that.
沃克
Walker,
你见过这东西吗?
do you know anything about this?
没有 先生
No, sir.
我一整天没来前面了
I've not been out in the front all day.
丘比特夫人来过这儿吗?
Has Mrs. Cubitt been out here?
这我也不知道 是吧 先生?
I've no way of knowing, have I, sir?
等我抄完 我希望你能把这儿擦干净
When I've done this, I want you to wash it off,
别跟任何人说 直接来找我
and tell no one about it, and then come to me.
我需要你帮我送封急信
I shall have an urgent letter for you to post.
艾尔西?
Elsie?
艾尔西
Elsie,
你在干吗?
what are you doing?
我正在找你
I was looking for you.
我想刚才是开门的声音
I thought I heard the door.
你今天出门了吗 出这房子了吗?
Have you been out today, out of the house?
希尔顿 上床去吧
Hilton, come to bed,
一觉睡醒什么都会好的
everything will look better in the morning.
那些画也会好?
Will the drawings look better?!
那些跳舞的小人也会好?
Will the dancing men look better?!
你干吗为这些涂鸦大惊小怪?
Why do they fuss you so?
我大惊小怪?
Fuss me?!
不过是玩笑 孩子的恶作剧
They're just a joke, a bit of mischief!
月正中天
The moon's high.
在美国 人们说这样的月亮会让人发狂
Where I come from, they say a moon like that drives you crazy.
去旅行好吗 希尔顿 离开这儿好吗?
Why don't we travel, Hilton, why don't we go away?
我爱这儿 跟我爱你一样
I love this place as much as I love you.
希尔顿...
Hilton-
你看到什么了?
What did you see?
没什么 什么都没有
Nothing, nothing at all!
不要去 亲爱的
Please, dearest.
希尔顿 求你了
Hilton, I beg you!
外面有人
There's somebody outside.
希尔顿
Hilton!
希尔顿 等等
Hilton, wait!
你会干出伤人的事的
You'll come to harm!
你就不担心他会干出伤人的事?
Or are you afraid he will come to harm?!
这两个一模一样
These two are identical.
是啊
Yes.
我把那个擦掉过
Well, I had that one washed off,
这肯定是后来又画上去的
then it must have reappeared.
要是你看清楚那家伙就好了
You know, it's a pity you didn't get a closer look at this chap.
要是她没拦着我
If only she hadn't tried to stop me.
我从来没冲她发过脾气
I've never been angry with her before,
可她知道外头那人是谁 这我肯定
but she knew who was out there, of that I'm sure.
她也知道这些小人是什么意思
And she knows what these figures mean.
这些是不是只是后来加上去的内容
Was this a mere addition to this,
还是说这两个是两条不同的信息?
or did it appear to be entirely separate?
这个是画在另一块门板上的
That was on a separate panel of the door.
好吧 我知道我该做什么了
Well, I know what I'm going to do,
我该回家
I shall go home,
跟我的人在树林里守株待兔
sit with half a dozen of my lads in the shrubbery,
要是再看到这家伙露面
and if this fellow calls again,
打他个屁滚尿流 以后再也别来烦我们
give him such a thrashing he'll leave us alone in the future.
这倒也是个办法
Well, that would be one way.
丘比特先生 这案子有隐情 绝不可草率
Mr. Cubitt, this case is too deep for such a simple remedy.
我得走了 不然要错过火车了
I must go now if I'm to catch my train.
我可不会让艾尔西一个人晚上待着
I'd not leave Elsie alone at night.
艾尔西
Elsie!
没错
Quite right.
走好 丘比特先生
Good day, Mr. Cubitt.
我们一两天就会去见你了 耐心点
We will join you in a couple of days, and be patient!
再见 华生大夫
Good bye, Dr. Watson.
不用你送我了
I'll find my own way.
再见
Bye.
我可看不出来你有同情心
You weren't exactly sympathetic.
他不是要我同情他的
He doesn't come to me for sympathy.
很有挑战性
It is a considerable challenge.
安静才能让我更好的工作
I shall work better for silence.
那好吧
Oh, well,
我敢说我也能找到些安静的事去做
I dare say I can find something quiet to do.
吁
Whoa, sit.
你在哪儿找到的这个?
Where did you find this?
就在院子里长椅边上
Down by the garden bench.
那是不是说
Will that, uh, mean
你要让我再送一封信去伦敦了 先生?
you'll be wanting me to take another letter for London, sir?
是吗?
Very well.
要赶最后一班车 我得马上动身
I'll have to get a move on if I'm gonna catch the last post.
沃克 让你做什么你再做什么
Walker, just do what you're told!
什么事 华生?
Yes, Watson?
我想你可能会想看泰晤士报 福尔摩斯
Uh, I thought you might like the Times, Holmes.
你认为我进展如何?
What do you make of my progress?
也没弄出个所以然来 对吧?
Well, it still doesn't mean very much, does it?
多的足够让我给美国发个电报了
Quite enough for me to send a telegram to the United States.
"ABESLANE" 这是什么意思?
What on earth does that mean, "ABESLANE"?
华生 想想 要是这是E
Watson, if this is E,
手拿旗子表示单词结束
flag denotes the end of words.
这松鸡太好吃了
Mm, this grouse is superb.
哈德逊太太可是超常发挥了这回
Mrs. Hudson has really surpassed herself this time.
最晚一班去马特洛克的火车是几点?
What time is the last train to Matlock?
恐怕我们错过了
I'm afraid we've missed it.
福尔摩斯 我真希望你能吃上一口
Holmes, I do wish you would try and eat a bite.
我只需要美国方面给我个回信
I just need an answer to my telegram from America,
来龙去脉就搞清楚了
and the story is complete.
亚伯 我想留下 我要留下
Abe, I wanna stay, and I'm going to stay.
那你在芝加哥的朋友怎么办?
What about your friends in Chicago?
你的家人怎么办?
What about your family?!
你管他们叫朋友?
Friends do you call them;
一帮子凶手 劫匪 勒索犯 那算什么家?
killers, robbers, extortionists, some family.
可咱们两个订婚了
But you and I were engaged!
对不起 亚伯 那是父亲强迫我答应的
I'm sorry, Abe, my father forced me into it.
跟你过那种生活 要我怎么能开心?
How could I be happy with you in that life?!
请你离开吧 求你了 我求你了
Please go away, please, I beg you.
你求我?
You beg me?!
是
Yes.
希尔顿这么好
Hilton is such a good man.
要是让他卷入丑闻 我会心碎的
It would break my heart if scandal ever touched him.
给你钱
Here's money,
都在这儿了
it's all that I have.
不
No!
你要跟我回家
You're coming home!
不
No!
你得跟我回去
You're coming home!
不
No!
真他...
What the-
不
No!
华生?
Watson?
该死的 出什么事了?
What the devil is going on?
你的电报有回音了?
An answer to your telegram?
不 是希尔顿丘比特的另一封信
No, it's another letter from Hilton Cubitt.
"艾尔西
"ELSIE
准...备"
PRE-P ARE."
"艾尔西 准备 见上"
ELSIE-RE-ARE-TO-MEET-THY-GO
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes, sir.
多谢
Thank you.
芝加哥警局的威尔逊哈格里夫
It's from Wilson Hargreave, of the Chicago Police Bureau.
"如您所问"
"In reply to your inquiry,
"亚伯斯拉内是芝加哥最险恶的人之一"
Abe Slaney is one of the most dangerous men in Chicago. "
快走 快走
Come along, come along.
有辆车
There's a cab!
去瑞都岭镇庄园 上车吗?
Ridling Thorpe Manor, gentlemen?
越快越好
As fast as you can!
你怎么知道?
How do you know?
我打赌你是伦敦来的法医 先生
Bet you're the surgeon from London, sir.
对不起 你干吗...
I beg your pardon, what makes you-
她还没死 先生
She's not dead yet, sir.
你也许能救她 不过她还是要上绞架的
You may be able to save her, but she's for the gallows.
绞架?
The gallows?!
没错 先生 她杀了自己的丈夫
Right, sir, she murdered her husband.
我想 来的是警长和医生吧
Inspector of Police, and Doctor of Medicine, I perceive?
的确如此 我是达比郡警署的探长马丁
Yes, indeed, Inspector Martin, Darbyshire Constabulary.
我是医生卡休
And I am Dr. Carthew, the surgeon.
先生们 这边请
This way, gentlemen.
这位是夏洛克福尔摩斯先生
This is Mr. Sherlock Holmes,
我是他的朋友兼同事华生大夫
and I am his friend and colleague, Dr. Watson.
福尔摩斯先生 这事你又知道些什么呢?
Mr. Holmes, but what do you know of this business?!
不少
A good deal.
希尔顿丘比特先生 曾是我的客户
Mr. Hilton Cubitt was my client.
可这案子今天凌晨三点才发生的
But the crime was only committed at 3:00 o'clock this morning.
你在伦敦是怎么听到风声的
How could you hear of it in London
我前脚进 你后脚就到了?
and get to the spot as soon as I?
我预料到了
I anticipated it.
我们原打算来阻止这一切
We came in hope of preventing it.
那你一定是拿到了
Then you must have important evidence
我不知道的证据了
of which I am ignorant.
只有跳舞的小人为证
Only the evidence of the dancing men.
跳舞的小人?
The dancing men?
我稍后会跟你解释
I will explain all that to you later.
既然我们已经无法阻止悲剧
Since we are too late to prevent this tragedy,
我一定要保证正义得到伸张
I am anxious to insure that justice is done.
您愿意协助我调查
Will you associate me in your investigation,
还是更乐意让我独自行动?
or will you prefer that I should act independently?
我很荣幸能和您协同办案 福尔摩斯先生
I should be proud for us to work together, Mr. Holmes.
但丑话说在前面 看起来没什么东西好调查的
But I must warn you, there seems very little to investigate.
希尔顿丘比特先生心脏中弹 已经死亡
Mr. Hilton Cubitt has been shot through the heart and he's dead.
那丘比特夫人呢?
And Mrs. Cubitt?
重伤
Seriously wounded.
子弹穿过头顶
The bullet passed through the front of her brain,
至今昏迷不醒
and she's still unconscious.
请 先生们
Excuse me, gentlemen.
只发现了一把枪 就在两个人中间
Only one gun has been found, lying on the floor between them.
共开了两枪
Two bullets have been fired.
福尔摩斯先生 我冒昧地说句
With respect, Mr. Holmes,
看上去一目了然 丘比特太太杀了她丈夫
it seems quite clear that Mrs. Cubitt murdered her husband
然后又掉转了枪口
and then turned the gun upon herself.
可他们是这么相亲相爱的一对
But they were a most devoted couple!
谋杀现场在这边的屋子 福尔摩斯先生
The murder room is through here, Mr. Holmes.
不用 我想先问问这里的佣人
No, I would like to start by interviewing the servants.
我请您 不要
And I beg you, nothing,
千万不要移动任何东西
absolutely nothing is to be moved.
厨房是从这儿走吗?
Is this the way to the kitchen?
我得说这案子肯定是
I should think it must have happened about
早上三点发生的 先生
3:00 o'clock in the morning, sir.
你们的房间在哪儿?
Where are your rooms?
顶楼 先生
On top, sir.
阁楼
The attics!
我被那声可怕的"砰"惊醒了
I was awoke by this terrible bang,
只能用爆炸来形容
an explosion is the only word.
大约过了一分钟...
And about a minute later-
还没到一分钟
It was less than a minute.
...又传来"砰"的一声 不过没那么响
-there was another bang, only not so loud.
你们做什么了?
What did you do?
我们下楼了 先生
We came downstairs, sir,
以为丘比特先生也会起身
expecting to find Mr. Cubitt up and about,
追逐窃贼或是发现哪儿着了火
chasing burglars or the house on fire, or-
但是卧室门开着
And the bedroom door was open.
我们看看了 发现屋子空着 就下来了
We looked in but the bed was empty so we came on down.
到处是烟
There was smoke,
越往下气味越重
and the smell was worse down here.
气味?
Smell?
啊 你是说枪的硝烟味?
Ah, you mean of the gunpowder?
我想就是 先生 是的
I suppose it was, sir, yes.
刚才你说越往下气味越重
Now, you say the smell was worse downstairs.
你在楼上也能闻到硝烟的味儿?
Could you also smell gunpowder upstairs?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
我提醒您 探长
I commend that fact
需要十分留意这一点
very carefully to your attention, Inspector.
金太太
Mrs. King,
您愿意坐下来谈吗 金太太?
would you like to sit down, Mrs. King?
那么 您到书房的时候 书房的门是开着的吗?
Now, was the library door open when you reached it?
开着的 先生
Open, yes, sir.
我们能看到桌上还亮着蜡烛 就走进去了
We could see the candle alight on the table and so we came in.
接着 哦 天啊
Then, oh dear,
那是我见过最可怕 也最怕见到的一幕
as terrible a thing as ever I saw or ever fear to see.
她受了重伤 先生
She was terrible wounded, sir.
不停地呻吟
She was moaning and groaning,
然后就瘫倒在地上
then she sort of collapsed on the floor
之后就再也没能开口说话
and she hasn't said anything since.
桑德斯?
Saunders?
我们把她抬到了卧室 先生
We moved her to her bedroom, sir,
然后让福瑞德沃克去叫了医生和警察
and sent Fred Walker for the doctor and the police.
没有发现破门而入的痕迹 或是潜入的人?
And there was no sign of a break-in, or of an intruder?
没有 先生
No, sir.
所有的门和窗都是锁上的
And all the doors and windows was locked,
就跟我们去就寝时一样
as we had left them when we went to bed.
探长...
Inspector...
哦 好的
Oh, yes...
除了可怜的丘比特夫人
Apart from poor Mrs. Cubitt,
你们没有动过其他东西?
nothing else has been moved?
没有 先生
No, sir.
没有 我们什么都没碰 福尔摩斯先生
No, we've touched nothing, Mr. Holmes.
谢谢你们 那么我们继续吧
Thank you. Then I think we can proceed.
几乎是顷刻毙命 可以这么假定
Almost instantaneous death, presumably.
直穿心脏
Mm, straight through the heart.
子弹还在里面
The bullet's still there.
那颗伤了丘比特夫人的子弹呢?
What about the bullet that wounded Mrs. Cubitt?
也还在她体内呢
That's still in her, as well.
得找个比我灵活的人才能取出来
It will take hands more nimble than mine to move it.
这是丘比特夫人的手提袋吗?
Is this Mrs. Cubitt's handbag?
没错 福尔摩斯先生
Yes, it is, Mr. Holmes.
至少有20张50磅的钞票
At least twenty 50-pound notes,
用钱打发不走
a bribe that failed.
看来 开了两枪
So, two bullets fired,
一死一伤 您所言不虚
two wounds inflicted, as you said.
是啊 大夫
Yes, Doctor.
那么你打算如何解释
Then how do you account for the bullet
这颗明显击中了窗框的子弹?
that has so obviously struck the window frame?
真想不到 你是怎么看到的?
By George, however did you see that?!
因为我来找了 卡休医生
Because, Dr. Carthew, I looked for it.
太厉害了 那子弹 怎么会 还在里头
Wonderful, why, the bullet's still there!
那么说一共是开了三枪了
So a third shot must have been fired.
也就是说 当时还有第三个人在场了
Which means that a third person must have been present.
一点不假
Exactly!
你们昨晚进到这间屋子
When you came into this room last night,
看到房门稍开 窗户也是开着的吗?
you say that the door was ajar; was not that window also open?
我不知道 先生 我想
I don't know, sir.
不是 先生
No, sir.
是关着的
It was shut.
桑德斯 你们跟厨师去书房等着好吗
Saunders, will you and Cook wait in the library,
还有你 沃克
and you, Walker.
卡休医生 你可以把尸体移走了
Dr. Carthew, you may remove the body.
看来是丘比特夫人自己关的窗
It was Mrs. Cubitt herself who shut that window.
要是桑德斯跟厨师在楼上就闻到了硝烟味
If Saunders and the Cook smelled smoke and gunpowder upstairs,
那肯定这儿的风不小
then there must have been a strong through draft.
不然的话 不会这么快
Otherwise, it would not have spread so quickly
就传到楼上去了
through the house.
我们知道那扇门是开着的
We know that door was open,
那么那扇窗户 一定也是开着的
that window, too, must also have been open,
不过只开了一会儿
but only for a short time.
为什么说只开了一会儿?
Why only for a short time?
因为烛火还没融化边缘
Because the candles have not gutted.
不然会流下烛泪来的
There is no trail of wax.
精彩 精彩
Wonderful, wonderful!
要是丘比特先生生前
If the late Mr. Hilton Cubitt
开的那枪 射中了窗框
fired the bullet which pierced the window frame,
那他一定是冲着
he must have been aiming at
要么站在屋内的人
someone who was standing either inside
要么就是个在窗外的人
or just outside the window.
谢谢 探长
Oh, thank you, Inspector.
那就是说 让丘比特先生送命的那颗子弹
Which means that the bullet which killed Mr. Cubitt
有可能是...
could have been fired by-
探长 我们真是英雄所见略同啊
Inspector, your thoughts and mine agree entirely.
这就是那颗
This is the cartridge case
杀了希尔顿丘比特先生的子弹上的弹壳
of the bullet which killed Mr. Hilton Cubitt.
福尔摩斯
Holmes,
要是共开了三枪
if three shots were fired,
为什么金太太跟桑德斯只听到了两声枪响?
why did Mrs. King and Saunders only hear two shots?
她们说了实情 可惜没意识到这是谎话
They were telling the truth, but lied without realizing it.
我可有点听不明白了
I'm not sure that I follow you.
你还记得金太太说的
You remember what Mrs. King said,
"我被一声巨响惊醒了 只能用"
"I was awoken by this terrible bang, an explosion,
"爆炸来形容"
it is the only word.
"过了一分钟"
And then a minute later
"又听到了一次较低的声响"
there was another bang but not so loud. "
第一次巨响其实是几乎同时射出的两枪
The first bang was two shots, fired almost simultaneously;
一枪从窗外射进来 杀了希尔顿丘比特
one from the window, which killed Hilton Cubitt,
另一枪是希尔顿丘比特打的
and one from Hilton Cubitt,
射偏打中了窗框
which missed and went into the window frame.
那第三枪?
And the third shot?
哀莫过于此 丘比特夫人
The saddest of all, Mrs. Cubitt,
绝望之下 欲饮弹自尽
self-administered in her despair.
你们谁知道这附近有一家旅馆
Now, do any of you know of an inn in the neighborhood
叫艾尔里奇?
called Elrige's?
有个农场主姓这个姓 离这儿几英里远
There's a farmer of that name, lives some miles off,
往...马尔布鲁克方向
in the direction of, uh, Milbrook.
偏僻的农场?
Is it a lonely farm?
非常偏 先生
Very lonely, sir.
那会不会有可能
Then it is just possible
昨晚这儿发生的一切
that the news of what happened here last night
还没传到那儿去
has not reached them.
说不定 先生
Maybe not, sir.
太棒了
Excellent!
沃克
Walker,
我想让你把这个便条
I want you to take this note
交给艾尔里奇农场的亚伯斯拉内
to a Mr. Abe Slaney of Elrige's Farm.
别说是我写的便条
Do not say that the note is from me,
也不要提到昨晚这儿发生的事
and make no mention of what happened here last night.
明白了吗?
Now, you understand?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
谢谢你 沃克
Thank you, Walker.
我预料会有人被我的便条邀来的
I am expecting a visitor in answer to my note.
桑德斯 他会来见丘比特夫人
Now, Saunders, he will ask for Mrs. Cubitt.
我要你带他到这儿来
I want you to show him into this room.
还要这房子看上去一切正常
I want this house to look quite normal,
你对所发生之事务必只字不提
and you must not give anything away of what has happened.
好的 先生
Very good, sir.
好了 我建议你们还是各司其职去吧
Now, I suggest you return to your duties.
而卡休医生 我建议您去照看您的病人
And, Dr. Carthew, I suggest you return to your patient.
对了 金太太
Oh, Mrs. King,
您的女主人是无辜的
your mistress is quite innocent.
你是怎么解开密码的?
But how did you break the code?
你看看
Well, you see,
一切密文的破解之路
the rules which guide us in deciphering all secret writing
都在于字母E
depend on the fact that E,
E是英语中最常见的字母
E is the most common letter in the English language.
所以 可想而知 我们真走运
So, you see, we were very fortunate
因为丘比特夫人名叫艾尔西
that Mrs. Cubitt's name was Elsie,
在第二张字条里颇为明显
and that it featured in the second message,
这样不光破解了字母E 还破解了L S跟I
which gave us not only the E, but the L, the S and the I.
而接下来的
Now, next, it seemed likely to us
两张字条像是提到了
that two of the messages were appeals of some sort
丘比特先生
to Mrs. Cubitt...
...加上T和G 字条写的就是:
...by adding the T and the G, the message reads:
"在艾尔里奇 过来 艾尔西"
"AT ELRIGE'S, COME ELSIE."
要是这个亚伯斯拉内就是凶手
Well, if this Abe Slaney is indeed the murderer,
我们得立即行动逮捕他
we must make an immediate move to arrest him.
不用慌张 探长
Calm yourself, Inspector.
我想他随时都会来
I expect him here at any moment.
可斯拉内怎么会来这儿?
But why should Slaney come here?
因为我写信要他来
Because I have written and asked him.
可他不会起疑心吗?
But won't his suspicions be roused?
难道他不想逃跑吗?
Will he not try to escape?
桑德斯?
Saunders?
打扰了 先生 有位先生往这边来了
Excuse me, sir, there's a gentleman approaching the house.
你觉得他带枪了吗?
Do you think he'd be armed?
傻子才不带
He's a fool if he's not.
您好 先生
Good day, sir.
丘比特夫人在吗?
Is Mrs. Cubitt at home?
我会为您通报 先生 请您进来
I'll inquire, sir, if you'll step inside.
请问您尊姓大名?
What name shall I say?
就说是个老朋友  她在等我
Tell her it's an old friend. She's expecting me.
请您在书房稍等片刻
If you'll wait in the library a moment.
好吧 先生们 看来你们是占到上风了
Well, gentlemen, it looks like you've got the drop on me,
不过谁能告诉这是怎么回事?
but what the hell is going on?
我想你就是亚伯斯拉内
Abe Slaney, I believe.
是有怎么样 你又是哪根葱?
What if I am, and who are you, anyway?
我的名字并不重要
My name would mean nothing to you,
不过我想芝加哥警局的威尔逊哈格里夫
though I suspect that of Wilson Hargreave
这个名字你该知道吧
of the Chicago Police Department, will.
啊 看来的确知道
Ah, I see that it does.
斯拉内先生 你该知道
Mr. Slaney, you should know
艾尔西丘比特伤势正重
that Mrs. Elsie Cubitt is very seriously ill.
鬼才信你
I don't believe you.
这话骗小孩差不多
This is some cheap trick.
艾尔西丘比特夫人一小时前刚给我写了张字条
Mrs. Elsie Cubitt wrote me a note just an hour ago,
只有我才看得懂的字条
a note that only I can understand.
若想人不懂 除非己莫写
What one man can invent, another can discover:
"我来了 亚伯斯拉内 在艾尔里奇 来吧艾尔西"
"I'M HERE, ABE SLANEY. AT ELRIGE'S, COME ELSIE."
你最后一张字条是
And your last note to her:
"艾尔西 准备见上帝吧"
"ELSIE PREPARE TO MEET THY GOD."
而这张
And this.
是你写的?
You wrote that note?
你说艾尔西受伤是骗我的
But you were lying about Elsie.
斯拉内 你开枪打死希尔顿丘比特之后
Slaney, when you shot and killed Hilton Cubitt,
艾尔西丘比特 伤心欲绝 想一死了之
Elsie Cubitt, in her despair, attempted to kill herself,
现在还很危险
and is now at death's door.
不
No.
不 我要见她
No, I gotta see her!
我得见她 我爱她 天地良心 艾尔西
I gotta see her, I love her, for God's sake, Elsie!
我爱你 艾尔西
I love you, Elsie!
艾尔西 艾尔西
Elsie, Elsie!
我相信她从美国远走高飞就是为了躲开你
I believe that she fled from America to avoid you.
而你尾随而来 让她经历了丧夫之痛
Because you followed her and made her life a misery,
她还不得不面对
she now lies under grave suspicion
谋杀亲夫的严重嫌疑
of murdering the husband she loved.
至少你可以为她洗清罪名
The least you can do is to clear her of that.
我想我目前能做到的就是
I guess the very best case I can make for myself now
把赤裸裸的真相 告诉你们
is to tell you the absolute, naked truth.
我有责任警告你
It is my duty to warn you
这会作为对你不利的证据
that it will be used against you.
我想你也许知道
I guess you probably know
艾尔西的父亲是芝加哥最有势力的人
that Elsie's father's the most powerful man in Chicago.
是芝加哥最有势力的犯罪分子之一
One of the most powerful criminal men in Chicago.
就是他发明的跳舞小人
It was he who invented the dancing men.
以前我们用来做暗号
We used it as a code in the old days.
艾尔西还是个孩子时 我就认识她
I've known Elsie since she was a child.
我和她订了婚
She was promised to me.
我可能是威胁了她
I may have threatened her,
可我绝不会碰她一根头发的
but I wouldn't have touched a hair on her pretty head.
不过你说的对 她痛恨芝加哥的一切
But you're right, she hated the whole Chicago business.
所以她就跑到欧洲去了
That's why she ran away to Europe.
直到她嫁给了这个英国佬
It was only after her marriage to this Englishman
我才发现了她的行踪
that I was able to find out where she was.
我写信给她 可没收到回信
I wrote to her, but I got no answer.
她把信烧了
She burned your letter.
她在达比郡这儿过得很开心
She was happy in her new life in Darbyshire.
我来英国是为了带她回家的
I came here to England to take her home!
我给她留了言
I sent her notes.
为了哄艾尔西回家 我想尽办法
I did everything I could to coax Elsie away,
结果丧失了理智 我开始威胁她
then my temper got the better of me and I began to threaten her.
不过昨天她给我写了回信
But yesterday she sent me a letter!
她说等到他丈夫睡去之后 会下楼来
She said she would come down when her husband was asleep
在书房尽头的窗户跟我谈谈
and speak to me through the end window
要是我就这么离开 让她静静地生活就好了
if I would go away afterwards and leave her in peace.
难道你还不明白吗?
Can I make you see?
我从没像跟他在一起这样快乐过
I've never been so happy as I've been here with him.
我爱他
I love him.
亚伯 我想留下 我要留下
Abe, I wanna stay, and I'm going to stay.
那你芝加哥的朋友怎么办?
What about your friends in Chicago?
你的家人怎么办?
What about your family?!
你管他们叫朋友?
Friends do you call them;
一帮子凶手 劫匪 勒索犯 那算什么家?
killers, robbers, extortionists, some family.
可咱们两个订婚了
But you and I were engaged!
对不起 亚伯 那是父亲强迫我答应的
I'm sorry, Abe, my father forced me into it.
跟你过那种生活 要我怎么能开心?
How could I be happy with you in that life?!
请你离开吧 求你了 我求你了
Please go away, please, I beg you.
你求我?
You beg me?!
是
Yes.
希尔顿这么好
Hilton is such a good man.
要是让他卷入丑闻 我会心碎的
It would break my heart if scandal ever touched him.
给你钱
Here's money,
都在这儿了
it's all that I have.
请你走吧
Now, please go away.
不
No!
你要跟我回家
You're coming home!
不
No!
你得跟我回去
You're coming home!
不
No!
真他...
What the-
不
No!
我想我们听得够多了 走吧
I think we've heard enough for the moment, come along.
走之前能让我看看她吗?
Can't I see her before I go?
谁也不能去看她
Nobody can see her,
连我们都没这权利
even we have not been given that privilege.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes,
我希望要是我再碰上什么大案
I hope that if ever again I have an important case,
还能交好运 有你帮助
I shall have the good fortune to have you by my side.
再会了 十分感谢
Good afternoon, and thank you.
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
你那字条写的是什么?
What did you write in that note?
看看你懂吗?
See if you could read it.
"立-刻-赶-来"
"COME-HERE-AT-ONCE,"
"立刻赶来"
"COME HERE AT ONCE."
这也太简单了点
How absurdly simple.
就这样 跳舞的小人们
And so the dancing men,
在为恶多年后
which had so often been the agents of evil,
终于站到了正义的一边
were finally used on the side of justice.
亚伯斯拉内在达比法庭被判死刑
Abe Slaney was condemned to death at the Darby assizes,
但他被改判为终身监禁
but his sentence was changed to penal servitude
因为有特殊情形
in consideration of mitigating circumstances
是希尔顿丘比特先生先开的枪
in the certainty that Hilton Cubitt had fired the first shot.
丘比特夫人彻底恢复了健康
Mrs. Cubitt made a complete recovery,
一直住在瑞都岭镇庄园
and lives still at Ridling Thorpe Manor.